I'm Dr. David Hanson, and I build robots with character.
أنا دكتور ديفيد هانسون، ومهنتي هي بناء روبوتات لديها شخصية.
And by that, I mean
وبذلك، أعني
that I develop robots that are characters,
أنني أبني روبوتات لديها شخصية،
but also robots that will eventually
وأيضاً روبوتات ستقوم في نهاية المطاف
come to empathize with you.
بالتعاطف معكم.
So we're starting with a variety of technologies
إذاً نحن نبدأ بباقة متنوعة من التكنلوجيات
that have converged into these conversational character robots
التي تلاقت في هذه الروبوتات من النوعية التي لديها شخصية تتحدث
that can see faces, make eye contact with you,
التي يمكنها رؤية الوجوه، تقوم بالتواصل معكم عبر العيون،
make a full range of facial expressions, understand speech
تقوم بمجموعة كاملة من تعابير الوجه، تفهم المحادثة،
and begin to model how you're feeling
وتبدأ تصميم نموذج لمشاعرك،
and who you are, and build a relationship with you.
وشخصيتك، وتبني علاقة معكم.
I developed a series of technologies
قمت بتطوير سلسلة من التكنلوجيات
that allowed the robots to make more realistic facial expressions
التي أتاحت للروبوتات بالقيام بالمزيد من تعابير الوجه الحقيقية
than previously achieved, on lower power,
عن التي أُنجزت سابقاً، تستخدم طاقة قليلة،
which enabled the walking biped robots, the first androids.
الأمر الذي مكّن الروبوتات ذوات الرجلين من المشي، أول أنواع الأندريودات(نوع روبوت).
So, it's a full range of facial expressions
إذاً، فهي مجموعة واسعة من تعابير الوجه
simulating all the major muscles in the human face,
تحاكي كل العضلات الرئيسية في وجه الإنسان،
running on very small batteries,
وتعمل على بطاريات صغيرة للغاية،
extremely lightweight.
وزنها خفيف جداً.
The materials that allowed the battery-operated facial expressions
المواد التي أتاحت تعابير الوجه التي تعمل بالبطاريات
is a material that we call Frubber,
هي مواد نطلق عليها Frubber،
and it actually has three major innovations
وفي الواقع لديها ثلاث إبتكارات رئيسية
in the material that allow this to happen.
في المواد التي تسمح لهذا أن يحصل.
One is hierarchical pores,
واحد هي هرمية المسام.
and the other is a macro-molecular nanoscale porosity in the material.
والآخر هو الجزيئية الكلية المسامية في المواد النانومترية الحجم.
There he's starting to walk.
ها هو يبدأ المشي.
This is at the Korean Advanced Institute of Science and Technology.
كان هذا في المعهد الكوري للعلوم التكنلوجيا المتقدمة.
I built the head. They built the body.
قمت ببناء الرأس. وقاموا ببناء الجسد.
So the goal here is to achieve sentience in machines,
إذا الهدف هنا هو تحقيق إحساس في الآلات ،
and not just sentience, but empathy.
وليس فقط إحساس، لكن تعاطف أيضاً.
We're working with the Machine Perception Laboratory
نتعاون مع مختبر تصوّر الآلة
at the U.C. San Diego.
في جامعة كالفورنيا في سان دياغو.
They have this really remarkable facial expression technology
لديهم هذه التكنلوجيا المدهشة لتعابير الوجه
that recognizes facial expressions,
التي تتعرف على تعابير الوجه،
what facial expressions you're making.
أي تعابير وجه تقوم بها.
It also recognizes where you're looking, your head orientation.
وتتعرف أيضاً على أين تنظر و إتجاه وجهك.
We're emulating all the major facial expressions,
نحن نحاكي كل تعابير الوجه الرئيسية،
and then controlling it with the software
وبعد ذلك نتحكم فيها بالبرمجيات
that we call the Character Engine.
التي نطلق عليها ماكينة الشخصية.
And here is a little bit of the technology that's involved in that.
وها هنا القليل عن التكنلوجيا التي تدخل في ذلك الأمر.
In fact, right now -- plug it from here, and then plug it in here,
في الواقع، حالياً -- نوصلها من هنا، ومن هنا،
and now let's see if it gets my facial expressions.
والآن لنرى اذا ما كانت ستعرف تعابير وجهي .
Okay. So I'm smiling.
حسناً. أنا أبتسم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now I'm frowning.
الآن أنا عابس .
And this is really heavily backlit.
وهذه حقاً خلفية قوية جداً.
Okay, here we go.
حسناً، لنبدأ.
Oh, it's so sad.
أوه، أنه حزين جداً.
Okay, so you smile, frowning.
حسناً، مبتسم جداً، عابس.
So his perception of your emotional states
إذاً فلديه تصوّر لحالات أحاسيسك
is very important for machines to effectively become empathetic.
من المهم جداً للآلات أن تصبح عاطفية بفعالية.
Machines are becoming devastatingly capable
الآلات تصبح قادرة جداً
of things like killing. Right?
على أشياء كالقتل. صحيح؟
Those machines have no place for empathy.
تلك الآلات ليس لديها مكان للعاطفة.
And there is billions of dollars being spent on that.
وقد تم صرف مليارات الدولارات على ذلك.
Character robotics could plant the seed
الروبوتات ذات الشخصية يمكن أن تزرع البذرة
for robots that actually have empathy.
لروبوتات تملك عاطفة حقيقية.
So, if they achieve human level intelligence
إذاً، اذا حققت ذكاء بمستوى الإنسان
or, quite possibly, greater than human levels of intelligence,
أو، محتمل جداً، أكثر من معدلات ذكاء الإنسان،
this could be the seeds of hope for our future.
يمكن أن يُحدث هذا بذور أمل لمستقبلنا.
So, we've made 20 robots in the last eight years, during the course of getting my Ph.D.
إذاً، لقد صنعنا 20 روبوت في الثمان سنوات الأخيرة، خلال مدة حصولي على الدكتوراة.
And then I started Hanson Robotics,
وبعد ذلك أنشأت هانسون للروبوتات،
which has been developing these things for mass manufacturing.
التي كانت تطوّر هذه الأشياء للتصنيع الشامل.
This is one of our robots
هذا أحد الروبوتات خاصتنا
that we showed at Wired NextFest a couple of years ago.
الذي عرضناه في معرض Wired NextFest قبل عدة سنوات.
And it sees multiple people in a scene,
يرى عدة أشخاص في المشهد،
remembers where individual people are,
يتذكر أين كان الأفراد،
and looks from person to person, remembering people.
وينظر من شخص لشخص، متذكراً الناس.
So, we're involving two things.
إذاً، نحن ضالعون في شيئين.
One, the perception of people,
أولاً ، تصوّر الناس.
and two, the natural interface,
وثانياً، الواجهة الطبيعية،
the natural form of the interface,
الشكل الطبيعي للواجهة،
so that it's more intuitive for you to interact with the robot.
بحيث يصبح التفاعل مع الروبوتات أكثر سهولة.
You start to believe that it's alive and aware.
تبدأ بتصديق أنها حيّة وواعية.
So one of my favorite projects was bringing all this stuff together
لذا فأحد مشاريعي المفضلة كان تجميع كل هذه الأشياء سوياً
in an artistic display of an android portrait
في عرض فني لصورة الروبوت
of science-fiction writer Philip K. Dick,
لكاتب الخيال العلمي فيليب كي ديك،
who wrote great works like, "Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?"
الذي كتب أعمال عظيمة مثل، " هل يحلم أندرويد بخرفان إلكترونية؟"،
which was the basis of the movie "Bladerunner."
الذي كان أساس فليم "Bladerunner."
In these stories, robots often think
في هذه القصص، الروبوتات دائماً تفكّر
that they're human, and they sort of come to life.
بأنها إنسان. وهي نوع ما تأتي الى الحياة.
So we put his writings, letters,
إذاً نحن نضع كتاباته، رسائله،
his interviews, correspondences,
مقابلاته، مراسلاته،
into a huge database of thousands of pages,
في قاعدة بيانات ضخمة لآلاف الصفحات،
and then used some natural language processing
وبعد ذلك نستخدم معالجة اللغة الطبيعية
to allow you to actually have a conversation with him.
لتتيح لنا حقيقة بالقيام بمحادثه معه.
And it was kind of spooky, because he would say these things
وقد كانت نوع من الرعب. لأنه قد يقول تلك الأشياء
that just sounded like they really understood you.
التي بدت مثل أنهم فعلاً فهموا ما ترمي إليه.
And this is one of the most exciting projects that we're developing,
وهذا أحد المشاريع المثيرة للدهشة التي نقوم بتطويرها،
which is a little character that's a spokesbot
التي هي شخصية صغيرة تتحدث
for friendly artificial intelligence, friendly machine intelligence.
لذكاء إصطناعي محبب، ذكاء آلة محبب.
And we're getting this mass-manufactured.
وقد بدأنا في التصنيع الشامل.
We specked it out to actually be doable
نحن نجهزها لتصبح قابلة للتصنيع حقاً
with a very, very low-cost bill of materials,
مع تكلفة منخفضة جداً جداً من المواد،
so that it can become a childhood companion for kids.
بحيث تصبح رفيقة الطفولة للأطفال.
Interfacing with the Internet, it gets smarter over the years.
نوصلها مع الإنترنت، وتصبح أذكى مع مرور الوقت.
As artificial intelligence evolves, so does his intelligence.
ولأن الذكاء الإصطناعي يتطور، كذلك يتطور الذكاء.
Chris Anderson: Thank you so much. That's incredible.
كريس أندرسون: شكراً جزيلاً لك. هذا مذهل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)